<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>Applying_to_Graduate_School_in_Psychology</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/index.htm?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/index.htm?slide={{position}}" href-swf="/"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>Applying to Graduate School in Psychology: A Mini-Workshop</title>
		<content>Applying to Graduate School in Psychology: A Mini-Workshop Based on an invited Psi Chi panel presentation at the 83th Annual Meeting of the Eastern Psychological Association by John C. Norcross, Susan K. Whitbourne, Carlos A. Escoto, and Thomas P. Hogan,  Applying to Graduate School in Psychology: A Mini-Workshop Based on an invited Psi Chi panel presentation at the 83th Annual Meeting of the Eastern Psychological Association by John C. Norcross, Susan K. Whitbourne, Carlos A. Escoto, and Thomas P. Hogan,  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Preparing for Graduate School</title>
		<content>Preparing for Graduate School When should you start applying? Your first day of undergraduate classes! Begin exploring subfields you want to study. A year and a half out, identify faculty you want to study with. A year out, begin studying for the GRE. A year out, email faculty you want to study with and strike up a conversation. A year out, take the GRE A year out, begin writing purpose statement Six months out, ask faculty for letters of recommendation Six months out, complete application Most deadlines are mid- to late- December Notification in early- to mid- April Preparing for Graduate School When should you start applying? Your first day of undergraduate classes! Begin exploring subfields you want to study. A year and a half out, identify faculty you want to study with. A year out, begin studying for the GRE. A year out, email faculty you want to study with and strike up a conversation. A year out, take the GRE A year out, begin writing purpose statement Six months out, ask faculty for letters of recommendation Six months out, complete application Most deadlines are mid- to late- December Notification in early- to mid- April </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Preparing for Graduate School</title>
		<content>Preparing for Graduate School What do admissions committees look for? Specific psychology courses? Number of credits? Major? Some combination of these? Preparing for Graduate School What do admissions committees look for? Specific psychology courses? Number of credits? Major? Some combination of these? </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Preparing for Graduate School</title>
		<content>Preparing for Graduate School    Preparing for Graduate School    </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Course Prerequisites for Graduate Programs in Psychology</title>
		<content>Course Prerequisites for Graduate Programs in Psychology What courses do graduate programs require? Statistics? Research methods? Abnormal? Developmental? Cognitive? Social? Personality? Course Prerequisites for Graduate Programs in Psychology What courses do graduate programs require? Statistics? Research methods? Abnormal? Developmental? Cognitive? Social? Personality? </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Course Prerequisites for Graduate Programs</title>
		<content>Course Prerequisites for Graduate Programs    Course Prerequisites for Graduate Programs    </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Importance of Criteria in Admissions Decisions</title>
		<content>Importance of Criteria in Admissions Decisions What do admissions committees look for? GPA? GRE Scores? Letters of recommendation? Statement of purpose? Internship? Importance of Criteria in Admissions Decisions What do admissions committees look for? GPA? GRE Scores? Letters of recommendation? Statement of purpose? Internship? </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Importance of Criteria in Admissions Decisions</title>
		<content>Importance of Criteria in Admissions Decisions    Importance of Criteria in Admissions Decisions    </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>Final Selection Criteria PhD Admission Decision</title>
		<content>Final Selection Criteria PhD Admission Decision    Final Selection Criteria PhD Admission Decision    </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students</title>
		<content>Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students What about the GRE? How high? What’s average? What about my GPA? How high? What’s average? Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students What about the GRE? How high? What’s average? What about my GPA? How high? What’s average? </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students</title>
		<content>Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students  Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students</title>
		<content>For specific entrance requirements see Graduate Study in Psychology in the Bissell Library. Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students  For specific entrance requirements see Graduate Study in Psychology in the Bissell Library. Minimum Required and Actual GRE Scores of First-Year Graduate Students  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title></title>
		<content>
		</content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Median Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology</title>
		<content>Median Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology So how bleak is the admission picture? Easier for Masters than PhD. For Masters: Easier for Quantitative, Health, Counseling. Harder for Neuroscience, Cognitive, School. For PhD: Easier for Educational, School, Community. Harder for Clinical, Personality, Social. Median Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology So how bleak is the admission picture? Easier for Masters than PhD. For Masters: Easier for Quantitative, Health, Counseling. Harder for Neuroscience, Cognitive, School. For PhD: Easier for Educational, School, Community. Harder for Clinical, Personality, Social. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Mean Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology</title>
		<content>Mean Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology    Mean Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology    </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Median Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology – Clinical PSYCHOLOGY</title>
		<content>Median Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology – Clinical PSYCHOLOGY    Median Program Acceptance Rates in Psychology – Clinical PSYCHOLOGY    </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Mean Acceptance Rates and Financial Assistance</title>
		<content>Mean Acceptance Rates and Financial Assistance Will I receive financial aid? Almost all in a research-oriented PhD program receive tuition waiver and assistantship. But acceptance rate is very low. Half of applicants accepted to a free-standing PsyD program are accepted. But very few receive tuition waiver and/or assistantship.   97%  14% Mean Acceptance Rates and Financial Assistance Will I receive financial aid? Almost all in a research-oriented PhD program receive tuition waiver and assistantship. But acceptance rate is very low. Half of applicants accepted to a free-standing PsyD program are accepted. But very few receive tuition waiver and/or assistantship.   97%  14% </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>Identifying and Targeting Compatible Graduate Programs</title>
		<content>Identifying and Targeting Compatible Graduate Programs Job prospects are good. Through 2020, employment for psychologist expected to be faster than average for all occupations. Assumes PhD. Quick Facts: Psychologists (From Occupational Outlook Handbook)2010 Median Pay$68,640 per year &amp;#x0A;$33.00 per hour Entry-Level EducationSee How to Become OneWork Experience in a Related OccupationNoneOn-the-job TrainingInternship/residencyNumber of Jobs, 2010174,000Job Outlook, 2010-2022% (Faster than average)Employment Change, 2010-2037,700  Identifying and Targeting Compatible Graduate Programs Job prospects are good. Through 2020, employment for psychologist expected to be faster than average for all occupations. Assumes PhD. Quick Facts: Psychologists (From Occupational Outlook Handbook)2010 Median Pay$68,640 per year &amp;#x0A;$33.00 per hour Entry-Level EducationSee How to Become OneWork Experience in a Related OccupationNoneOn-the-job TrainingInternship/residencyNumber of Jobs, 2010174,000Job Outlook, 2010-2022% (Faster than average)Employment Change, 2010-2037,700  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>Identifying and Targeting Compatible Graduate Programs</title>
		<content>Identifying and Targeting Compatible Graduate Programs Job prospects are good. Through 2020, employment for psychologists at universities and college expected to be average. School psychology projected to have greatest growth. Assumes PhD.  Quick Facts: Postsecondary Teachers (From Occupational Outlook Handbook)2010 Median Pay$62,050 per year Entry-Level EducationDoctoral or professional degreeWork Experience in a Related OccupationNoneOn-the-job TrainingNoneNumber of Jobs, 20101,756,000Job Outlook, 2010-2017% (About as fast as average)Employment Change, 2010-20305,700 Identifying and Targeting Compatible Graduate Programs Job prospects are good. Through 2020, employment for psychologists at universities and college expected to be average. School psychology projected to have greatest growth. Assumes PhD.  Quick Facts: Postsecondary Teachers (From Occupational Outlook Handbook)2010 Median Pay$62,050 per year Entry-Level EducationDoctoral or professional degreeWork Experience in a Related OccupationNoneOn-the-job TrainingNoneNumber of Jobs, 20101,756,000Job Outlook, 2010-2017% (About as fast as average)Employment Change, 2010-20305,700 </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="20" xmlns="">
		<title>Programs, Program, and Programs</title>
		<content>Programs, Program, and Programs What types of programs/training models are there? Research Scientist: Trained to be a research scholar. Programs in area of specialization. Fewer students in recent years. Usually at larger, Research 1 universities. See NRC Ranking of U.S. Psychology Ph.D. Programs for more detail. Programs, Program, and Programs What types of programs/training models are there? Research Scientist: Trained to be a research scholar. Programs in area of specialization. Fewer students in recent years. Usually at larger, Research 1 universities. See NRC Ranking of U.S. Psychology Ph.D. Programs for more detail. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000020.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="21" xmlns="">
		<title>Programs, Program, and Programs</title>
		<content>Programs, Program, and Programs What types of programs/training models are there? Scientist-Practitioner: Boulder model. Trained to be a researcher and clinical practitioner. Usually at non-Research 1 Universities. Smaller universities and colleges. Programs, Program, and Programs What types of programs/training models are there? Scientist-Practitioner: Boulder model. Trained to be a researcher and clinical practitioner. Usually at non-Research 1 Universities. Smaller universities and colleges. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000021.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="22" xmlns="">
		<title>Programs, Program, and Programs</title>
		<content>Programs, Program, and Programs What types of programs/training models are there? Practitioner: Vail model. PsyD. Trained to be a clinical practitioner and consumer of research. Usually at smaller universities and colleges. Can include for-profit institutions (e.g., Argosy, Nova Southeastern). Programs, Program, and Programs What types of programs/training models are there? Practitioner: Vail model. PsyD. Trained to be a clinical practitioner and consumer of research. Usually at smaller universities and colleges. Can include for-profit institutions (e.g., Argosy, Nova Southeastern). </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000022.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="23" xmlns="">
		<title>Choices, Choices, Choices</title>
		<content>Choices, Choices, Choices Research Scientist: Select program based on experts in field of interest. Read their work. Consider library facilities, research space, computer access, and research funding. Choices, Choices, Choices Research Scientist: Select program based on experts in field of interest. Read their work. Consider library facilities, research space, computer access, and research funding. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000023.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="24" xmlns="">
		<title>Choices, Choices, Choices</title>
		<content>Choices, Choices, Choices Practitioner: Determine amount of practica available. Who are the supervisors? Where are placements? Who are the clients? What is the theoretical orientation? Choices, Choices, Choices Practitioner: Determine amount of practica available. Who are the supervisors? Where are placements? Who are the clients? What is the theoretical orientation? </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000024.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="25" xmlns="">
		<title>Other Considerations</title>
		<content>Other Considerations Apply to a range of programs. Sure thing to long shots. Don’t rule out a move of state. Consider non-accredited programs if not accepted. Some maybe too new.  See when they may be. Compare curricula to accredited programs. Locally for Clinical Psychology IUP (PhD). PSU-Erie (MA in Clinical) Locally for Counseling Psychology Carlow (PsyD). Chatham (PsyD). See APA.org for all accredited programs. Other Considerations Apply to a range of programs. Sure thing to long shots. Don’t rule out a move of state. Consider non-accredited programs if not accepted. Some maybe too new.  See when they may be. Compare curricula to accredited programs. Locally for Clinical Psychology IUP (PhD). PSU-Erie (MA in Clinical) Locally for Counseling Psychology Carlow (PsyD). Chatham (PsyD). See APA.org for all accredited programs. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000025.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="26" xmlns="">
		<title>Personal Statements and Admission Interviews</title>
		<content>Personal Statements and Admission Interviews Personal statements are very important. Ranks with GPA and GREs for PhD programs. Interview Critical hurdle after others have been cleared. Vary by type of program. Purpose:  Fit for program. Personal Statements and Admission Interviews Personal statements are very important. Ranks with GPA and GREs for PhD programs. Interview Critical hurdle after others have been cleared. Vary by type of program. Purpose:  Fit for program. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000026.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="27" xmlns="">
		<title>Personal Statement</title>
		<content>Personal Statement aka: Statement of objectives. Statement of goals. Tailor it to the individual program. Do not submit a generic statement. Carefully follow guidelines on format, etc. Proofread; get others to read and comment. Personal Statement aka: Statement of objectives. Statement of goals. Tailor it to the individual program. Do not submit a generic statement. Carefully follow guidelines on format, etc. Proofread; get others to read and comment. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000027.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="28" xmlns="">
		<title>Personal Statement</title>
		<content>Personal Statement Topics include: Career plans. General interests. Research experience. Academic objectives. Internship/practicum experience. Academic background. Motivation. Faculty interests. Special skills. Personal Statement Topics include: Career plans. General interests. Research experience. Academic objectives. Internship/practicum experience. Academic background. Motivation. Faculty interests. Special skills. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000028.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="29" xmlns="">
		<title>Personal Statement</title>
		<content>Personal Statement AVOID in personal statement: Humor. Hyperbole. Hard luck. Personal Statement AVOID in personal statement: Humor. Hyperbole. Hard luck. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000029.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="30" xmlns="">
		<title>Pre-Interview</title>
		<content>Pre-Interview Clean up your electronic persona! Voice mail. Face Book. Email signature. Web page. Pre-Interview Clean up your electronic persona! Voice mail. Face Book. Email signature. Web page. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000030.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="31" xmlns="">
		<title>Pre-Interview</title>
		<content>Pre-Interview Check out the department, faculty. Do practice interviews. BE ON TIME! Pre-Interview Check out the department, faculty. Do practice interviews. BE ON TIME! </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000031.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="32" xmlns="">
		<title>Interview</title>
		<content>Interview Dress: Guys: Suit coat, tie, white or light-colored shirt. Dress shoes, dark socks. NO piercings. Cover tattoos. Gals: Pants suit or dress and blouse. No high heels. No plunging necklines/see through blouses. Easy on makeup, perfume and jewelry. Interview Dress: Guys: Suit coat, tie, white or light-colored shirt. Dress shoes, dark socks. NO piercings. Cover tattoos. Gals: Pants suit or dress and blouse. No high heels. No plunging necklines/see through blouses. Easy on makeup, perfume and jewelry. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000032.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="33" xmlns="">
		<title>Other Interview Issues</title>
		<content>Other Interview Issues Almost always you pay for the travel cost. Topics often the same as personal statement. Have your own questions ready. Remember, you have cleared many hurdles, this is your opportunity to shine. Other Interview Issues Almost always you pay for the travel cost. Topics often the same as personal statement. Have your own questions ready. Remember, you have cleared many hurdles, this is your opportunity to shine. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000033.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="34" xmlns="">
		<title>Applying to Graduate School and securing letters of recommendation</title>
		<content>Applying to Graduate School and securing letters of recommendation Based on an invited Psi Chi panel presentation at the 83th Annual Meeting of the Eastern Psychological Association by John C. Norcross Applying to Graduate School and securing letters of recommendation Based on an invited Psi Chi panel presentation at the 83th Annual Meeting of the Eastern Psychological Association by John C. Norcross </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000034.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="35" xmlns="">
		<title>The fundamentals</title>
		<content>The fundamentals BA/BS (4.6 full-time years) MA/MS/MSW/Med (2 full-time years) PsyD (4.5 full-time years, including internship) PhD (6 – 7.58 full-time years) The fundamentals BA/BS (4.6 full-time years) MA/MS/MSW/Med (2 full-time years) PsyD (4.5 full-time years, including internship) PhD (6 – 7.58 full-time years) </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000035.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="36" xmlns="">
		<title>Psychology degrees awarded</title>
		<content>Psychology degrees awarded   100,000 undergraduate degrees in psychology/year 20,000 MA/MS in psychology /year 6,000 PhD/PsyD in psychology/year Psychology degrees awarded   100,000 undergraduate degrees in psychology/year 20,000 MA/MS in psychology /year 6,000 PhD/PsyD in psychology/year </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000036.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="37" xmlns="">
		<title>The reasons you are applying</title>
		<content>The reasons you are applying Why? Cost is substantial Application fees $15-$100 for baccalaureate degree $35 for Masters $50 for Ph.D. On average, total cost to apply to grad school is $1,000 excluding travel Be sure to request a fee waiver if in dire financial straits Competition is stiff especially for a clinical Ph.D. Make sure you REALLY want to go Apply wisely The reasons you are applying Why? Cost is substantial Application fees $15-$100 for baccalaureate degree $35 for Masters $50 for Ph.D. On average, total cost to apply to grad school is $1,000 excluding travel Be sure to request a fee waiver if in dire financial straits Competition is stiff especially for a clinical Ph.D. Make sure you REALLY want to go Apply wisely </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000037.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="38" xmlns="">
		<title>The application year</title>
		<content>The application year Attack the process with drive and commitment Emulate the manic zeal of successful med school applicants Your professional future is (literally) at stake An intense process requiring at least the workload of another 3-credit college course Position yourself for a busy Fall (because you cannot wait for winter break) Take the application process seriously (or not at all) The application year Attack the process with drive and commitment Emulate the manic zeal of successful med school applicants Your professional future is (literally) at stake An intense process requiring at least the workload of another 3-credit college course Position yourself for a busy Fall (because you cannot wait for winter break) Take the application process seriously (or not at all) </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000038.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="39" xmlns="">
		<title>Typical components of Grad school application</title>
		<content>Typical components of Grad school application Application form Transcripts GRE scores Application fees Personal statement List of psychology courses Curriculum vitae Letters of recommendation Typical components of Grad school application Application form Transcripts GRE scores Application fees Personal statement List of psychology courses Curriculum vitae Letters of recommendation </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000039.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="40" xmlns="">
		<title>Application form</title>
		<content>Application form Each grad school has its own form; psychology has not yet adopted a universal or common application Begin at least 3 months before deadline; otherwise, you will be rushed and working on tight schedule Approximately one-half of applications are now online Useful to print a copy of the application General rules: type all applications and materials; check typing, grammar and spelling; complete several drafts; ask faculty to review them; professional and neat as possible. Application form Each grad school has its own form; psychology has not yet adopted a universal or common application Begin at least 3 months before deadline; otherwise, you will be rushed and working on tight schedule Approximately one-half of applications are now online Useful to print a copy of the application General rules: type all applications and materials; check typing, grammar and spelling; complete several drafts; ask faculty to review them; professional and neat as possible. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000040.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="41" xmlns="">
		<title>Transcripts</title>
		<content>Transcripts Secure an unofficial copy of your transcript prior to applying Request Registrar’s Office of all attended colleges mail an official copy of your transcript directly to the graduate school Cost of transcripts averages $5 to $12 per copy Submit transcript requests at least 1 month before the deadline Transcripts Secure an unofficial copy of your transcript prior to applying Request Registrar’s Office of all attended colleges mail an official copy of your transcript directly to the graduate school Cost of transcripts averages $5 to $12 per copy Submit transcript requests at least 1 month before the deadline </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000041.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="42" xmlns="">
		<title>GRE Scores</title>
		<content>GRE Scores GRE score reports are electronically sent to the 4 graduate schools you list Score reports sent 4 – 6 weeks after the test date Grad programs require official ETS transmission, not a copy of your personal score report Additional score reports from ETS - $25 each ETS pledges to “make every effort to send your score reports within 10 working days after receipt of your request” but you should allow for at least 1 month GRE scores can be transmitted during a 5-year period GRE Scores GRE score reports are electronically sent to the 4 graduate schools you list Score reports sent 4 – 6 weeks after the test date Grad programs require official ETS transmission, not a copy of your personal score report Additional score reports from ETS - $25 each ETS pledges to “make every effort to send your score reports within 10 working days after receipt of your request” but you should allow for at least 1 month GRE scores can be transmitted during a 5-year period </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000042.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="43" xmlns="">
		<title>Application fees</title>
		<content>Application fees Range from $10 to $100 per program Average $35 for masters programs and $50 for doctoral programs Only 7% of graduate schools let you apply for free Total cost of applying to 10-12 graduate schools will run $1,000 (excluding travel for interview) If in dire financial need, request a fee waiver Application fees Range from $10 to $100 per program Average $35 for masters programs and $50 for doctoral programs Only 7% of graduate schools let you apply for free Total cost of applying to 10-12 graduate schools will run $1,000 (excluding travel for interview) If in dire financial need, request a fee waiver </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000043.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="44" xmlns="">
		<title>Personal statements</title>
		<content>Personal statements To be masterfully covered in detail in a few minutes by Dr. Thomas P. Hogan Personal statements To be masterfully covered in detail in a few minutes by Dr. Thomas P. Hogan </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000044.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="45" xmlns="">
		<title>List of Psychology Courses</title>
		<content>List of Psychology Courses Undergraduate Psychology Courses Course #			Course Title										Credits			Professor					Grade Psych 110		Fundamental of Psychology				3				Dr. Freud						B+ Psych 210		Statistics													3				Dr. Skinner					B+ Psych 310		Research Methods								3				Dr. Gilligan					B Psych 330L		Research Methods Lab						3				Dr. Rogers					A- Psych 390		Career Development Seminar			1				Dr. Abnormal				current List of Psychology Courses Undergraduate Psychology Courses Course #			Course Title										Credits			Professor					Grade Psych 110		Fundamental of Psychology				3				Dr. Freud						B+ Psych 210		Statistics													3				Dr. Skinner					B+ Psych 310		Research Methods								3				Dr. Gilligan					B Psych 330L		Research Methods Lab						3				Dr. Rogers					A- Psych 390		Career Development Seminar			1				Dr. Abnormal				current </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000045.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="46" xmlns="">
		<title>Curriculum vitae</title>
		<content>Curriculum vitae Typically optional but research suggests you should include it Like a resume, but CVs designed for graduate schools and academic positions CVs go on for several pages and don’t list objectives Several CV formats are presented in the Insider’s Guide Never fabricate, but perhaps embellish appropriately Avoid any polarizing information (e.g., political parties, radical interests, religious affiliations) Include References only with person’s permission Curriculum vitae Typically optional but research suggests you should include it Like a resume, but CVs designed for graduate schools and academic positions CVs go on for several pages and don’t list objectives Several CV formats are presented in the Insider’s Guide Never fabricate, but perhaps embellish appropriately Avoid any polarizing information (e.g., political parties, radical interests, religious affiliations) Include References only with person’s permission </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000046.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="47" xmlns="">
		<title>Letters of recommendation</title>
		<content>Letters of recommendation Admission Committees seek a personal, outside look at your work from someone experienced in the field More objective sense of certain skills and characteristics than GPAs and GREs can provide Several terms used for these people: references, recommenders, referees Research demonstrates the high importance of letters Program directors rate recommendations the single most important criterion in their admissions decisions Yet students routinely underestimate their value At least 3 letters for graduate school Letters of recommendation Admission Committees seek a personal, outside look at your work from someone experienced in the field More objective sense of certain skills and characteristics than GPAs and GREs can provide Several terms used for these people: references, recommenders, referees Research demonstrates the high importance of letters Program directors rate recommendations the single most important criterion in their admissions decisions Yet students routinely underestimate their value At least 3 letters for graduate school </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000047.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="48" xmlns="">
		<title>Write your own letter</title>
		<content>Write your own letter Our favorite expression to students requesting letters of recommendation In figurative sense, your behavior over past 3 years largely determines what we will write about you Your behavior dictates our letter on your behalf Think of your professors as mirrors and recorders of your activity Once you accept this premise, you immediately recognize your power – you largely control what goes in your letter Write your own letter Our favorite expression to students requesting letters of recommendation In figurative sense, your behavior over past 3 years largely determines what we will write about you Your behavior dictates our letter on your behalf Think of your professors as mirrors and recorders of your activity Once you accept this premise, you immediately recognize your power – you largely control what goes in your letter </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000048.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="49" xmlns="">
		<title>Most frequent applicant characteristics on recommendation form</title>
		<content>Most frequent applicant characteristics on recommendation form Motivated and hardworking High intellectual/scholarly ability Research skills Emotionally stable and mature Writing skills Speaking skills Teaching skills/potential Works well with others Creative and original Strong knowledge of the area of study Character or integrity Special skills, such as computer or lab Most frequent applicant characteristics on recommendation form Motivated and hardworking High intellectual/scholarly ability Research skills Emotionally stable and mature Writing skills Speaking skills Teaching skills/potential Works well with others Creative and original Strong knowledge of the area of study Character or integrity Special skills, such as computer or lab </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000049.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="50" xmlns="">
		<title>The don’ts</title>
		<content>The don’ts Don’t blame your poor performance on other people Don’t publically manifest your pitiful skills in time management Don’t exhibit any lethal student behaviors (e.g., substance abuse, unethical behavior, interpersonal problems, lack of motivation) Don’t ask inappropriate folks for letters of recommendation (e.g., relatives, politicians, psychotherapists) Don’t assume faculty MUST write you a letter The don’ts Don’t blame your poor performance on other people Don’t publically manifest your pitiful skills in time management Don’t exhibit any lethal student behaviors (e.g., substance abuse, unethical behavior, interpersonal problems, lack of motivation) Don’t ask inappropriate folks for letters of recommendation (e.g., relatives, politicians, psychotherapists) Don’t assume faculty MUST write you a letter </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000050.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="51" xmlns="">
		<title>A dozen do’s</title>
		<content>A dozen do’s Do start early 	Ask for letters at least 6 weeks before the deadline 	Provide reference forms 4-6 weeks before deadline Do ask the right people (most valuable source of letter in descending order) 	Mentor with whom the applicant has done considerable work 	The applicant’s professor, who is well-known and respected 	An employer in a job related to the applicant’s professional goals 	The chair of department in which the applicant is majoring 	A professor who taught a relevant upper-division course A dozen do’s Do start early 	Ask for letters at least 6 weeks before the deadline 	Provide reference forms 4-6 weeks before deadline Do ask the right people (most valuable source of letter in descending order) 	Mentor with whom the applicant has done considerable work 	The applicant’s professor, who is well-known and respected 	An employer in a job related to the applicant’s professional goals 	The chair of department in which the applicant is majoring 	A professor who taught a relevant upper-division course </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000051.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="52" xmlns="">
		<title>A dozen Do’s</title>
		<content>A dozen Do’s Do ask if the person can write you a “good” letter of recommendation 	Be assertive and specific in your request Do waive your right 	A confidential letter carries more weight Do get organized 	Final impression of referee is your request and your packet information Do provide materials to improve tone and detail of letter A dozen Do’s Do ask if the person can write you a “good” letter of recommendation 	Be assertive and specific in your request Do waive your right 	A confidential letter carries more weight Do get organized 	Final impression of referee is your request and your packet information Do provide materials to improve tone and detail of letter </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000052.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="53" xmlns="">
		<title>A Dozen Do’s</title>
		<content>A Dozen Do’s  A Dozen Do’s  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000053.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="54" xmlns="">
		<title>A dozen do’s</title>
		<content>A dozen do’s Do all these steps in person Do prepare for electronic submission letters Do practice self-empathy Do complete the annoying information on recommendation forms (return address) Do double-check everything Do stay in touch with recommenders A dozen do’s Do all these steps in person Do prepare for electronic submission letters Do practice self-empathy Do complete the annoying information on recommendation forms (return address) Do double-check everything Do stay in touch with recommenders </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000054.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="55" xmlns="">
		<title>Individualize our advice</title>
		<content>Individualize our advice  Individualize our advice  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000055.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="56" xmlns="">
		<title>You write your own letter (reprise)</title>
		<content>You write your own letter (reprise) Your behavior dictates the tone and content of your letter Start writing your own enthusiastic and detailed letter of recommendation NOW! You write your own letter (reprise) Your behavior dictates the tone and content of your letter Start writing your own enthusiastic and detailed letter of recommendation NOW! </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000056.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="57" xmlns="">
		<title>Writing personal statements</title>
		<content>Writing personal statements Based on an invited Psi Chi panel presentation at the 83th Annual Meeting of the Eastern Psychological Association by Thomas P. Hogan,  Writing personal statements Based on an invited Psi Chi panel presentation at the 83th Annual Meeting of the Eastern Psychological Association by Thomas P. Hogan,  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000057.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="58" xmlns="">
		<title>Students’ common questions</title>
		<content>Students’ common questions Is it important? Use same one for all applications? What should I cover? Students’ common questions Is it important? Use same one for all applications? What should I cover? </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000058.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="59" xmlns="">
		<title>Why so much anxiety?</title>
		<content>Why so much anxiety? Different names Different lengths Different topics And of course, you have to compose it as opposed to transcripts, letters of recommendation, GRE scores Why so much anxiety? Different names Different lengths Different topics And of course, you have to compose it as opposed to transcripts, letters of recommendation, GRE scores </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000059.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="60" xmlns="">
		<title>Some samples (Watch changes in titles, requests)</title>
		<content>Some samples (Watch changes in titles, requests) School A Statement of Goals Please include a statement of approximately 1,000 – 1,500 words concerning your plans for graduate study and a professional career. Please be as specific as possible about (a) the development of your academic interest in psychology and reasons for pursuing the PhD (b) past research experience and current research interests (c) clinical experience (if applicable) (d) special ability and skills (e.g., programming, assessment, neuroimaging) (e) long term career goals, and (f) why you have chosen to apply to the University of XXXXX Department of Psychology and how your interests fit with the research program of the faculty member(s) whom you indicated on the application form. Some samples (Watch changes in titles, requests) School A Statement of Goals Please include a statement of approximately 1,000 – 1,500 words concerning your plans for graduate study and a professional career. Please be as specific as possible about (a) the development of your academic interest in psychology and reasons for pursuing the PhD (b) past research experience and current research interests (c) clinical experience (if applicable) (d) special ability and skills (e.g., programming, assessment, neuroimaging) (e) long term career goals, and (f) why you have chosen to apply to the University of XXXXX Department of Psychology and how your interests fit with the research program of the faculty member(s) whom you indicated on the application form. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000060.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="61" xmlns="">
		<title>School B</title>
		<content>School B Statement of Academic Purpose Describe yourself in a way that would give us more of an opportunity to know you as a person. Why do you wish to study at the XXXXXX? If there are any aspects of your background or experience that were not already mentioned, and that would contribute to the desired diversity of the Institute, please indicate. What are your career goals and reasons for undertaking doctoral studies? School B Statement of Academic Purpose Describe yourself in a way that would give us more of an opportunity to know you as a person. Why do you wish to study at the XXXXXX? If there are any aspects of your background or experience that were not already mentioned, and that would contribute to the desired diversity of the Institute, please indicate. What are your career goals and reasons for undertaking doctoral studies? </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000061.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="62" xmlns="">
		<title>School C</title>
		<content>School C Statement of Purpose Write a personal statement that describes (1) your career goals and how they evolved. (2) research experiences and other psychology-related experiences you have had that have helped you prepare you for graduate schools, and (3) research interests you would like to pursue in graduate school and why you feel XXXX fits these interests. Feel free to include any additional information that you think would help us to understand your strengths as an applicant for graduate study. Suggested length 400-700 words. Faculty interest: Applications may list up to five faculty members with whom they would like to work, but they are not required to do so. This section of the application is optional, However, if you are applying to the Clinical Psychology Program, please list at least one member of the Core Faculty who you believe could serve as your primary mentor. School C Statement of Purpose Write a personal statement that describes (1) your career goals and how they evolved. (2) research experiences and other psychology-related experiences you have had that have helped you prepare you for graduate schools, and (3) research interests you would like to pursue in graduate school and why you feel XXXX fits these interests. Feel free to include any additional information that you think would help us to understand your strengths as an applicant for graduate study. Suggested length 400-700 words. Faculty interest: Applications may list up to five faculty members with whom they would like to work, but they are not required to do so. This section of the application is optional, However, if you are applying to the Clinical Psychology Program, please list at least one member of the Core Faculty who you believe could serve as your primary mentor. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000062.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="63" xmlns="">
		<title>School d</title>
		<content>School d Personal and Research Statements On the following pages, please write your Personal Statement (up to 500 words) and your Research Statement (up to 500 words) in the space provided. Personal Statement: Please include your reasons for pursuing a degree in psychology, including ultimate career goals. Research Statement: Please include your research interests and potential faculty person(s) with whom you would like to further develop these interests. School d Personal and Research Statements On the following pages, please write your Personal Statement (up to 500 words) and your Research Statement (up to 500 words) in the space provided. Personal Statement: Please include your reasons for pursuing a degree in psychology, including ultimate career goals. Research Statement: Please include your research interests and potential faculty person(s) with whom you would like to further develop these interests. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000063.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="64" xmlns="">
		<title>Is the personal statement important</title>
		<content>Is the personal statement important YES!!! It ranks only after letters of recommendation in importance for doctoral programs Ranks third for master’s programs Is the personal statement important YES!!! It ranks only after letters of recommendation in importance for doctoral programs Ranks third for master’s programs </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000064.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="65" xmlns="">
		<title>Kisses of death (Appleby &amp; Appleby, 2007)</title>
		<content>Kisses of death (Appleby &amp;amp; Appleby, 2007) Not doing your homework (often shows up in the personal statement) Damaging personal statements Academic problems Faulty letters of recommendation Lack of writing skills Misfired attempts to impress Kisses of death (Appleby &amp;amp; Appleby, 2007) Not doing your homework (often shows up in the personal statement) Damaging personal statements Academic problems Faulty letters of recommendation Lack of writing skills Misfired attempts to impress </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000065.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="66" xmlns="">
		<title>And finally…</title>
		<content>And finally… You can check the APA’s Graduate Study in Psychology which provides ratings of importance, under “other criteria” for each program’s rating of importance for statement goals And finally… You can check the APA’s Graduate Study in Psychology which provides ratings of importance, under “other criteria” for each program’s rating of importance for statement goals </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000066.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="67" xmlns="">
		<title>Do same statement for all?</title>
		<content>Do same statement for all? NO!!! Customize for each program Examine watch program's request: 	What points to cover 	Format (e.g., words, pages) Follow those directions Do same statement for all? NO!!! Customize for each program Examine watch program's request: 	What points to cover 	Format (e.g., words, pages) Follow those directions </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000067.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="68" xmlns="">
		<title>What not to include</title>
		<content>What not to include Avoid the 3 H’s 	Humor – jokes, cuteness, a funny thing… 	Hyperbole – most, always, never, worst… 	Hard luck – terrible childhood, depression… What not to include Avoid the 3 H’s 	Humor – jokes, cuteness, a funny thing… 	Hyperbole – most, always, never, worst… 	Hard luck – terrible childhood, depression… </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000068.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="69" xmlns="">
		<title>Damaging personal statements</title>
		<content>Damaging personal statements Sub-themes 	Altruistic Personal Statement 		I just want to help everyone 	Excessive self-disclosure 		Being severely depressed myself… 	Nonspecific research goals 		I’m open to research in any area 	Professional inappropriateness 		I’m broke so I thought I’d go to grad school Damaging personal statements Sub-themes 	Altruistic Personal Statement 		I just want to help everyone 	Excessive self-disclosure 		Being severely depressed myself… 	Nonspecific research goals 		I’m open to research in any area 	Professional inappropriateness 		I’m broke so I thought I’d go to grad school </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000069.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="70" xmlns="">
		<title>General strategy</title>
		<content>General strategy Identify your focus for grad school Identify several of your major experiences (research, clinical, internships, etc.) Do one “boilerplate” with the first 2 points List what each program wants Research each program for areas of emphasis and faculty Modify the “boilerplate” to cover 4 and 5 PROOFREAD!!!! 	Get others to read 	After thoroughly vetted, if possible, have a faculty member or two react 	Remember it is used to assess your writing skills General strategy Identify your focus for grad school Identify several of your major experiences (research, clinical, internships, etc.) Do one “boilerplate” with the first 2 points List what each program wants Research each program for areas of emphasis and faculty Modify the “boilerplate” to cover 4 and 5 PROOFREAD!!!! 	Get others to read 	After thoroughly vetted, if possible, have a faculty member or two react 	Remember it is used to assess your writing skills </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000070.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
