<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document-metadata version="1.0" xmlns="http://breeze.macromedia.com/">
	<document-info>
		<title>Martin Chapter 5 - How to Be Fair to Science</title>
		<summary></summary>
		<author/>
		<keywords/>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
		<view-link href="/index.htm?slide={{position}}" href-html5="/index.htm?slide={{position}}" href-swf="/"/>
	</document-info>
	<section type="slide" position="1" xmlns="">
		<title>Chapter 5</title>
		<content>Chapter 5 How to Be Fair to Science Chapter 5 How to Be Fair to Science </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000001.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="2" xmlns="">
		<title>Outline</title>
		<content>Outline Ethical issues and scientific inquiry Fraud Plagiarism Safeguards APA Style Outline Ethical issues and scientific inquiry Fraud Plagiarism Safeguards APA Style </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000002.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="3" xmlns="">
		<title>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity</title>
		<content>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity To make research public, a written report is created. It describes: What was done,  What was found, and  How the findings were interpreted. Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity To make research public, a written report is created. It describes: What was done,  What was found, and  How the findings were interpreted. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000003.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="4" xmlns="">
		<title>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity</title>
		<content>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity Ethical issues can arise at this point. We’ll consider two such issues: Fraud, and Plagiarism. Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity Ethical issues can arise at this point. We’ll consider two such issues: Fraud, and Plagiarism. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000004.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="5" xmlns="">
		<title>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity</title>
		<content>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity APA has ethical standards that relate to fraud and plagiarism. Specifically, section 6.21 states: “Psychologists do not fabricate data or falsify results in their publications” and “If psychologists discover significant errors in their published data, they take reasonable steps to correct such errors in a correction, retractions, erratum, or other appropriate publication means.” Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity APA has ethical standards that relate to fraud and plagiarism. Specifically, section 6.21 states: “Psychologists do not fabricate data or falsify results in their publications” and “If psychologists discover significant errors in their published data, they take reasonable steps to correct such errors in a correction, retractions, erratum, or other appropriate publication means.” </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000005.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="6" xmlns="">
		<title>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity</title>
		<content>Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity In section 6.22, the APA specifies: “Psychologists do not present substantial portions or elements of another’s work or data as their own, even if the other work is cited occasionally.” Ethical Issues and Scientific Integrity In section 6.22, the APA specifies: “Psychologists do not present substantial portions or elements of another’s work or data as their own, even if the other work is cited occasionally.” </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000006.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="7" xmlns="">
		<title>Fraud in Science</title>
		<content>Fraud in Science Important to distinguish between error and fraud. An error is an honest mistake that occurs in the research process. Many opportunities for errors in research: In collecting data,  In scoring measures,  In entering data into a computer,  In publication typesetting. Fraud in Science Important to distinguish between error and fraud. An error is an honest mistake that occurs in the research process. Many opportunities for errors in research: In collecting data,  In scoring measures,  In entering data into a computer,  In publication typesetting. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000007.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="8" xmlns="">
		<title>Fraud in Science</title>
		<content>Fraud in Science Fraud is an explicit effort to deceive and misrepresent data. If a researcher makes up or changes data to support a hypothesis, this is fraud. The essential goal of science is to discover knowledge and reveal truth. Fraud the ultimate enemy of the scientific process.  Fraud in Science Fraud is an explicit effort to deceive and misrepresent data. If a researcher makes up or changes data to support a hypothesis, this is fraud. The essential goal of science is to discover knowledge and reveal truth. Fraud the ultimate enemy of the scientific process.  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000008.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="9" xmlns="">
		<title>The (Sad) Case of Diederik Stapel</title>
		<content>The (Sad) Case of Diederik Stapel Stapel was a prominent Dutch social psychologist. Research misconduct committed by Stapel was vast. involves manipulation of data and complete fabrication of entire experiments.  The fraudulent data used in at least 58 published, peer-reviewed papers. A number of dissertations are thought to be based on fabricated data.  Colleagues of In June 2013 Stapel agreed, in a settlement, to perform 120 hours of community service and to lose benefits associated with his former job equivalent to a year and a half's worth of salary.  He avoided further criminal prosecution. The (Sad) Case of Diederik Stapel Stapel was a prominent Dutch social psychologist. Research misconduct committed by Stapel was vast. involves manipulation of data and complete fabrication of entire experiments.  The fraudulent data used in at least 58 published, peer-reviewed papers. A number of dissertations are thought to be based on fabricated data.  Colleagues of In June 2013 Stapel agreed, in a settlement, to perform 120 hours of community service and to lose benefits associated with his former job equivalent to a year and a half's worth of salary.  He avoided further criminal prosecution. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000009.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="10" xmlns="">
		<title>Why Is Fraud in Science Committed?</title>
		<content>Why Is Fraud in Science Committed? The primary cause of fraud is the competitive nature of an academic career. There is strong pressure on researchers to have their research published.  Why Is Fraud in Science Committed? The primary cause of fraud is the competitive nature of an academic career. There is strong pressure on researchers to have their research published.  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000010.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="11" xmlns="">
		<title>Safeguards Against Fraud</title>
		<content>Safeguards Against Fraud Fortunately, several safeguards help keep fraud in check. Science is public. Other researchers read reports and conduct further studies, including replications. This is the primary means of revealing error and uncovering fraud in research. Safeguards Against Fraud Fortunately, several safeguards help keep fraud in check. Science is public. Other researchers read reports and conduct further studies, including replications. This is the primary means of revealing error and uncovering fraud in research. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000011.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="12" xmlns="">
		<title>Safeguards Against Fraud</title>
		<content>Safeguards Against Fraud A second safeguard against fraud is peer review.  Safeguards Against Fraud A second safeguard against fraud is peer review.  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000012.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="13" xmlns="">
		<title>Safeguards Against Fraud</title>
		<content>Safeguards Against Fraud Consequences of fraud: Suspension or firing,  Removal of a degree granted, Cancellation of funding for research, and  Forced return of monies paid from grants. Safeguards Against Fraud Consequences of fraud: Suspension or firing,  Removal of a degree granted, Cancellation of funding for research, and  Forced return of monies paid from grants. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000013.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="14" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism   Plagiarism   </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000014.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="15" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism To present someone else’s ideas or words as your own. Plagiarism, like fraud, is a serious breach of ethics. Plagiarism To present someone else’s ideas or words as your own. Plagiarism, like fraud, is a serious breach of ethics. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000015.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="16" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism Reference citations must be included in your paper. Done: Whenever someone else’s ideas or work has influenced your thinking and writing, Whenever you use direct quotations, Whenever you paraphrase someone else’s work. Plagiarism Reference citations must be included in your paper. Done: Whenever someone else’s ideas or work has influenced your thinking and writing, Whenever you use direct quotations, Whenever you paraphrase someone else’s work. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000016.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="17" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism If an idea or information you include in a paper is not originally yours, you must cite it. For students, the penalties for plagiarism may include: A failing grade on the paper or the course, and Expulsion from the institution. For faculty, the penalties for plagiarism are much the same as those for fraud. Plagiarism If an idea or information you include in a paper is not originally yours, you must cite it. For students, the penalties for plagiarism may include: A failing grade on the paper or the course, and Expulsion from the institution. For faculty, the penalties for plagiarism are much the same as those for fraud. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000017.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="18" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism Plagiarism can occur on a variety of different levels. At one extreme, you can literally copy an entire paper word for word and present it as your own work. In this case, the plagiarism is clearly a deliberate act committed with complete awareness. Plagiarism Plagiarism can occur on a variety of different levels. At one extreme, you can literally copy an entire paper word for word and present it as your own work. In this case, the plagiarism is clearly a deliberate act committed with complete awareness. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000018.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="19" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism Plagiarism can be much more subtle occurring without your direct knowledge or intent. After working on a project for an extended amount of time, it can be difficult to separate your own words and ideas from those that come to you from outside sources.   As a results your ideas and phrases can appear in your paper without appropriate citation  Plagiarism Plagiarism can be much more subtle occurring without your direct knowledge or intent. After working on a project for an extended amount of time, it can be difficult to separate your own words and ideas from those that come to you from outside sources.   As a results your ideas and phrases can appear in your paper without appropriate citation  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000019.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="20" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism Guidelines developed by Myers and Hansen (1997) can help prevent you from plagiarizing: Take complete notes, including:  Author’s name,  Year of publication,  Title of the article,  Journal name,  Volume number, and  Page numbers.   For books, include the publisher’s name and city. Plagiarism Guidelines developed by Myers and Hansen (1997) can help prevent you from plagiarizing: Take complete notes, including:  Author’s name,  Year of publication,  Title of the article,  Journal name,  Volume number, and  Page numbers.   For books, include the publisher’s name and city. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000020.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="21" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism Within your paper, identify the source of any ideas, words, or information that are not your own. Identify any direct quotes by quotation marks at the beginning and end of the quotes, and indicate where you got the quotes. Plagiarism Within your paper, identify the source of any ideas, words, or information that are not your own. Identify any direct quotes by quotation marks at the beginning and end of the quotes, and indicate where you got the quotes. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000021.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="22" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism Be careful about paraphrasing (restating someone else’s words).   It is tempting to lift whole phrases or catchy words from another source.   Use you own words instead, or use quotes.   Be sure to give credit to your source. Plagiarism Be careful about paraphrasing (restating someone else’s words).   It is tempting to lift whole phrases or catchy words from another source.   Use you own words instead, or use quotes.   Be sure to give credit to your source. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000022.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="23" xmlns="">
		<title>Plagiarism</title>
		<content>Plagiarism Include a complete list of references at the end of the paper.   References should include all the information listed in item 1 of this list (e.g., author’s name, journal name, etc.) If in doubt about whether a citation is necessary, cite the source anyway.   You will do no harm by being especially cautious. Plagiarism Include a complete list of references at the end of the paper.   References should include all the information listed in item 1 of this list (e.g., author’s name, journal name, etc.) If in doubt about whether a citation is necessary, cite the source anyway.   You will do no harm by being especially cautious. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000023.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="24" xmlns="">
		<title>APA Style</title>
		<content>APA Style APA Style </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000024.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="25" xmlns="">
		<title>APA Style: Journal Articles, One Author</title>
		<content>APA Style: Journal Articles, One Author Mellers, B. A. (2000). Choice and the relative pleasure of consequences. Psychological Bulletin, 126(6), 910-924. https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.126.6.910 Notice the font – Times New Roman (or Courier) is used Font size is 12-point. You may now use Calibri 11-pt., Ariel 11-pt., Lucida 10-pt., Sans Unicode 10-pt, Georgia 11-pt.,  The entry is double spaced. A hanging indent is used. The author’s last name is written followed by first initial and middle initial. Next comes the year the article was published. The title of the article is next. Only the first word in the title is capitalized. Next, the journal name is presented. All words in the journal name are capitalized and it is italicized. Next the volume number is presented. It is italicized. Then comes the issue number. Finally, the page numbers are presented. If the work has a doi, present it even if you read the printed (vs. online) version. Do not place a period at the end of the doi. APA Style: Journal Articles, One Author Mellers, B. A. (2000). Choice and the relative pleasure of consequences. Psychological Bulletin, 126(6), 910-924. https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.126.6.910 Notice the font – Times New Roman (or Courier) is used Font size is 12-point. You may now use Calibri 11-pt., Ariel 11-pt., Lucida 10-pt., Sans Unicode 10-pt, Georgia 11-pt.,  The entry is double spaced. A hanging indent is used. The author’s last name is written followed by first initial and middle initial. Next comes the year the article was published. The title of the article is next. Only the first word in the title is capitalized. Next, the journal name is presented. All words in the journal name are capitalized and it is italicized. Next the volume number is presented. It is italicized. Then comes the issue number. Finally, the page numbers are presented. If the work has a doi, present it even if you read the printed (vs. online) version. Do not place a period at the end of the doi. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000025.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="26" xmlns="">
		<title>Issue Numbers</title>
		<content>Issue Numbers If an article has an issue number, present it after the volume number. Do not italicize. Klimonski, R., &amp;amp; Palmer, S. (1993). The ADA and the hiring process in organizations. Consulting Psychology Journal: Practice and Research, 45(2), 10-36. https://doi.org/10.1037/1061-4087.45.2.10  Issue Numbers If an article has an issue number, present it after the volume number. Do not italicize. Klimonski, R., &amp;amp; Palmer, S. (1993). The ADA and the hiring process in organizations. Consulting Psychology Journal: Practice and Research, 45(2), 10-36. https://doi.org/10.1037/1061-4087.45.2.10  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000026.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="27" xmlns="">
		<title>Journal Articles, Two to 20 Authors</title>
		<content>Journal Articles, Two to 20 Authors Abbey, A., &amp;amp; Harnish, R. J. (1995). Perception of sexual intent: The role of gender, alcohol consumption and rape supportive attitudes. Sex Roles, 32, 297-313. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01544599  Harnish, R. J., Bridges, K. R., &amp;amp; Karelitz, J. E. (2017). Compulsive buying: Prevalence, irrational beliefs and purchasing. International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction, 15, 993-1007. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-016-9690-2  	 Note no issue numbers are available. Journal Articles, Two to 20 Authors Abbey, A., &amp;amp; Harnish, R. J. (1995). Perception of sexual intent: The role of gender, alcohol consumption and rape supportive attitudes. Sex Roles, 32, 297-313. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF01544599  Harnish, R. J., Bridges, K. R., &amp;amp; Karelitz, J. E. (2017). Compulsive buying: Prevalence, irrational beliefs and purchasing. International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction, 15, 993-1007. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11469-016-9690-2  	 Note no issue numbers are available. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000027.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="28" xmlns="">
		<title>Journal Articles, 21 or More Authors</title>
		<content>Journal Articles, 21 or More Authors If a reference has 21 or more authors, cite the first 19 authors, insert ellipsis (three periods) and then the last author. Wiskunde, B., Arslan, M., Fischer, P., Nowak, L., Van den Berg, O., Coetzee, L., Juárez, U., Riyaziyyat, E., Wang, C., Zhang, I., Li, P., Yang, R., Kumar, B., Xu, A., Martinez, R., McIntosh, V., Ibáñez, L. M., Mäkinen, G., Virtanen, E., . . . Kovács, A. (2019). Indie pop rocks mathematics: Twenty One Pilots, Nicolas Bourbaki, and the empty set. Journal of Improbable Mathematics, 27(1), 1935-1968. https://doi.org/10.0000/3mp7y-537  Journal Articles, 21 or More Authors If a reference has 21 or more authors, cite the first 19 authors, insert ellipsis (three periods) and then the last author. Wiskunde, B., Arslan, M., Fischer, P., Nowak, L., Van den Berg, O., Coetzee, L., Juárez, U., Riyaziyyat, E., Wang, C., Zhang, I., Li, P., Yang, R., Kumar, B., Xu, A., Martinez, R., McIntosh, V., Ibáñez, L. M., Mäkinen, G., Virtanen, E., . . . Kovács, A. (2019). Indie pop rocks mathematics: Twenty One Pilots, Nicolas Bourbaki, and the empty set. Journal of Improbable Mathematics, 27(1), 1935-1968. https://doi.org/10.0000/3mp7y-537  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000028.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="29" xmlns="">
		<title>Journal Articles without Volume and Page Numbers</title>
		<content>Journal Articles without Volume and Page Numbers Articles now are being available before they are available in specific issues of print or online-only journals. These will not have a volume or page numbers. To cite: Harnish, R. J., &amp;amp; Roster, C. A. (2018). The tripartite model of aberrant purchasing: A theory to explain the maladaptive pursuit of consumption. Psychology &amp;amp; Marketing. Advanced online publication. http://doi.org/10.1002/mar.21159  Journal Articles without Volume and Page Numbers Articles now are being available before they are available in specific issues of print or online-only journals. These will not have a volume or page numbers. To cite: Harnish, R. J., &amp;amp; Roster, C. A. (2018). The tripartite model of aberrant purchasing: A theory to explain the maladaptive pursuit of consumption. Psychology &amp;amp; Marketing. Advanced online publication. http://doi.org/10.1002/mar.21159  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000029.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="30" xmlns="">
		<title>Books</title>
		<content>Books To cite an entire book, present the author(s), followed by the year of publication, then the title (note first word and that followed by colon are capitalized), and then the publisher. If the book has a doi, present it next. Beck, C. A. J., &amp;amp; Sales, B. D. (2001).  Family mediation: Facts, myths, and future prospects. American Psychological Association. https://doi.org/10.1037/10401-000  Books To cite an entire book, present the author(s), followed by the year of publication, then the title (note first word and that followed by colon are capitalized), and then the publisher. If the book has a doi, present it next. Beck, C. A. J., &amp;amp; Sales, B. D. (2001).  Family mediation: Facts, myths, and future prospects. American Psychological Association. https://doi.org/10.1037/10401-000  </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000030.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="31" xmlns="">
		<title>Editions</title>
		<content>Editions If there are editions to the book, you must provide the edition number in the reference. Mitchell, T. R., &amp;amp; Larson, J. R. (1987).  People in organizations: An introduction to organizational behavior (3rd ed.). McGraw-Hill. Editions If there are editions to the book, you must provide the edition number in the reference. Mitchell, T. R., &amp;amp; Larson, J. R. (1987).  People in organizations: An introduction to organizational behavior (3rd ed.). McGraw-Hill. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000031.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="32" xmlns="">
		<title>Edited Books</title>
		<content>Edited Books To cite an edited book: Gibbs, J. T., &amp;amp; Huang, L. N. (Eds.). (1991). Children of color: Psychological interventions with minority youth. Jossey-Bass. Edited Books To cite an edited book: Gibbs, J. T., &amp;amp; Huang, L. N. (Eds.). (1991). Children of color: Psychological interventions with minority youth. Jossey-Bass. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000032.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="33" xmlns="">
		<title>Chapter in an Edited Book</title>
		<content>Chapter in an Edited Book To cite a chapter in an edited book: Bjork, R. A. (1989). Retrieval inhibition as an adaptive mechanism in human memory. In H. L. Roediger III &amp;amp; F. I. M. Craik (Eds.), Varieties of memory and consciousness (pp. 309-330). Erlbaum. Chapter in an Edited Book To cite a chapter in an edited book: Bjork, R. A. (1989). Retrieval inhibition as an adaptive mechanism in human memory. In H. L. Roediger III &amp;amp; F. I. M. Craik (Eds.), Varieties of memory and consciousness (pp. 309-330). Erlbaum. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000033.jpg"/>
	</section>
	<section type="slide" position="34" xmlns="">
		<title>Questions?</title>
		<content>Questions? Please email me. You may be tested on APA style. To help, please complete the reference exercises found on Canvas. Questions? Please email me. You may be tested on APA style. To help, please complete the reference exercises found on Canvas. </content>
		<related-content></related-content>
		<thumbnail href="data/thumb/thumb_slide_000034.jpg"/>
	</section>
</document-metadata>
